<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>Open Science Collaboration Blog</title><link href="http://osc.centerforopenscience.org/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="http://osc.centerforopenscience.org/feeds/ase-innes-ker.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>http://osc.centerforopenscience.org/</id><updated>2013-10-04T14:45:00-04:00</updated><entry><title>A publishing sting, but what was stung?</title><link href="http://osc.centerforopenscience.org/2013/10/04/a-publishing-sting-but-what-was-stung/" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2013-10-04T14:45:00-04:00</updated><author><name>Åse Innes-Ker</name></author><id>tag:osc.centerforopenscience.org,2013-10-04:2013/10/04/a-publishing-sting-but-what-was-stung/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Before Open Science there was Open Access (OA) — a movement driven by the
desire to make published research publicly accessible (after all, the public
usually had paid for it), rather than hidden behind paywalls.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Open Access is, by now, its very own strong movement — follow for example &lt;a href="http://bjoern.brembs.net/"&gt;Björn
Brembs&lt;/a&gt; if you want to know what is happening there — and 
there are now nice Open Access journals, like &lt;a href="http://www.plos.org/"&gt;PLOS&lt;/a&gt; and
&lt;a href="http://www.frontiersin.org/"&gt;Frontiers&lt;/a&gt;, which are
peer-reviewed and reputable. Some of these journals charge an article
processing fee for OA articles, but in many cases funders have introduced or
are developing provisions to cover these costs. (In fact, the big private
funder in Sweden INSISTS on it.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But, as always, situations where there is money involved and targets who are
desperate (please please please publish my baby so I won’t perish) breed mimics
and cuckoos and charlatans, ready to game the new playing field to their
advantage.  This is probably just a feature of the human condition (see
Triver’s “&lt;a href="http://www.amazon.com/The-Folly-Fools-Deceit-Self-Deception/dp/B008PGKA56"&gt;Folly of Fools&lt;/a&gt;”).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are lists of potentially predatory Open Access journals — I have linked
some in on my private blog (Åse Fixes Science)
&lt;a href="http://asefixesscience.wordpress.com/2013/04/14/open-access-watch-out-list/"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;
and
&lt;a href="http://asefixesscience.wordpress.com/2013/05/12/more-on-predatory-open-access/"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.
Reputation counts.  Buyers beware!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Demonstrating the challenges of this new marketplace, John Bohannon published
in Science (a decidedly not Open Access journal) a sting operation in which he
spoofed Open Access journals to test their peer-review system. The papers were
machine generated nonsense — one may recall the &lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sokal_affair"&gt;Sokal Hoax&lt;/a&gt; from the previous
Science Wars.  One may also recall the classic Ceci paper from 1982, which made
the rounds again earlier this year (and I blogged about that one too - &lt;a href="http://asehelene.wordpress.com/2013/05/31/music-social-proof-appeal-and-peer-review/"&gt;on my
other blog&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Crucially, all of Bohannon’s papers contained fatal flaws that a decent
peer-reviewer should catch. The big news? Lots of them did not (though PLOS
did). Here’s the &lt;a href="http://www.sciencemag.org/content/342/6154/60"&gt;Science&lt;/a&gt; article with
its &lt;a href="http://comments.sciencemag.org/content/10.1126/science.342.6154.60"&gt;commentary stream&lt;/a&gt;,
and a commentary from &lt;a href="http://retractionwatch.wordpress.com/2013/10/03/science-reporter-spoofs-hundreds-of-journals-with-a-fake-paper/"&gt;Retraction Watch&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is, of course, interesting — and it is generating buzz.  But, it is also
generating some negative reaction. For one, Bohannon did not include the
regular non-OA journals in his test, so the experiment lacks a control group,
which means we can make no comparison and draw no firm inferences from the
data. The reason he states (it is quoted on the Retraction Watch site) is the
very long turnaround times for regular journals, which can be months, even a
year (or longer, as I’ve heard). I kinda buy it, but this is really what is
angering the Open Access crowd, who sees this letter as an attempt to
implicate Open Access itself as the source of the problem. And, apart from
Bohannon not including regular journals in his test, Science published what he
wrote without peer reviewing it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My initial take? I think it is important to test these things — to uncover the
flaws in the system, and also to uncover the cuckoos and the mimics and the
gamers. Of course, the problems in peer review are not solely on the shoulders
of Open Access — Diederik Stapel, and other frauds, published almost
exclusively in paywalled journals (including Science).  The status of peer
review warrants its own scrutiny.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But, I think the Open Access advocates have a really important point to
make.  As noted on Retraction Watch, Bohannon's study didn't include
non-OA journals, so it's unclear whether the peer-review problems he
identified in OA journals are unique to their OA status.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I’ll end by linking in some of the commentary that I have seen so far — and, of
course, we’re happy to hear your comments.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The Guardian: &lt;a href="http://www.theguardian.com/higher-education-network/2013/oct/04/open-access-journals-fake-paper"&gt;Hundreds of Open Access journals accept fake science paper&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Peter Suber: &lt;a href="https://plus.google.com/109377556796183035206/posts/CRHeCAtQqGq"&gt;New “Sting” of Weak Open-Access Journals&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Curt Rice: &lt;a href="http://curt-rice.com/2013/10/04/what-science-and-the-gonzo-scientist-got-wrong-open-access-will-make-research-better/"&gt;What Science — and the Gonzo Scientist — got wrong&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The conversation: &lt;a href="http://theconversation.com/flawed-sting-operation-singles-out-open-access-journals-18846"&gt;Flawed sting operation&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The comics Grid: &lt;a href="http://blog.comicsgrid.com/2013/10/whos-afraid-open-access/"&gt;Who's afraid of Open Access&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Michael Eisen: &lt;a href="http://www.michaeleisen.org/blog/?p=1439"&gt;I confess, I wrote the Arsenic DNA paper to expose flaws in peer-review at subscription based journals&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://twitter.com/search?had_popular=true&amp;amp;q=JournalSting"&gt;#JournalSting&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/search?q=%23openaccess&amp;amp;src=hash"&gt;#openaccess&lt;/a&gt; on Twitter&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Sauropod Vertebra Picture of the week: &lt;a href="http://svpow.com/2013/10/03/john-bohannons-peer-review-sting-against-science/"&gt;John Bohannon’s peer-review sting against Science&lt;/a&gt;. (The last one is also collecting other links commenting on this paper - good resource).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</summary></entry></feed>