<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>Open Science Collaboration Blog</title><link href="http://osc.centerforopenscience.org/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="http://osc.centerforopenscience.org/feeds/osc.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>http://osc.centerforopenscience.org/</id><updated>2013-10-02T10:15:00-04:00</updated><entry><title>Welcome!</title><link href="http://osc.centerforopenscience.org/2013/10/02/welcome/" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2013-10-02T10:15:00-04:00</updated><author><name>OSC</name></author><id>tag:osc.centerforopenscience.org,2013-10-02:2013/10/02/welcome/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Welcome to the blog of the Open Science Collaboration! We are a loose network of researchers, professionals, citizen scientists, and others with an interest in open science, metascience, and good scientific practices.  We’ll be writing about:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Open science topics like reproducibility, transparency in methods and analyses, and changing editorial and publication practices&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Updates on open science initiatives like the &lt;a href="https://openscienceframework.org/reproducibility/‎"&gt;Reproducibility Project&lt;/a&gt; and opportunities to get involved in new projects like the &lt;a href="http://archivalproject.org/"&gt;Archival Project&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Interviews and opinions from researchers, developers, publishers, and citizen scientists working to make science more transparent, rigorous, or reproducible. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We hope that the blog will stimulate open discussion and help improve the way science is done!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you'd like to suggest a topic for a post, propose a guest post or column, or get involved with moderation, promotion, or technical development, we would love to hear from you! Email us at &lt;a href="mailto:oscbloggers@gmail.com"&gt;oscbloggers@gmail.com&lt;/a&gt; or tweet @OSCbloggers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The OSC is an open collaboration - anyone is welcome to join, contribute to discussions, or develop a project. The OSC blog is supported by the &lt;a href="http://centerforopenscience.org"&gt;Center for Open Science&lt;/a&gt;, a non-profit organization dedicated to increasing openness, integrity and reproducibility of scientific research.  &lt;/p&gt;</summary></entry></feed>